<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/static/xsl/clixdoc.xsl" ?>



<clix:documentation xmlns='http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml' xmlns:clix='http://bknr.net/clixdoc'>
  <clix:title>GDL/GWL 1.5 Documentation
  </clix:title>
 <clix:short-description>
How to use General-purpose Declarative Language to do "KBE" as well as
web applications to deploy those models.
  </clix:short-description>


 <h2><center>GDL/GWL 1.5 Documentation</center></h2>
 <center> <i>interim update for gdl1578</i> </center>

 <clix:chapter name="contents" title="Contents"></clix:chapter>
 <clix:contents></clix:contents>

<blockquote>

<clix:chapter name="abstract" title="Becoming an effective GDL developer">
<p>
Becoming effective with GDL consists of three (3) basic skills:

<ol>
<li> Editing text and managing files with Gnu Emacs (yes, other
editors will work, but Emacs provides special support and only Emacs
is supported by Genworks);
</li>

<li>
Very basic Common Lisp programming;
</li>

<li>
Writing Object Definitions in GDL itself, using the define-object macro.
</li>

</ol>
</p>

<p>
Beyond this, if you want to create nice Web applications with GDL, it
helps to know something about HTML and server-based computing. But
these concepts can be picked up over time and are not necessary to get
started or to make simple applications or 3D geometric objects.
</p>

   </clix:chapter>

 </blockquote>


 <clix:chapter name="install" title="Basic Installation">


<p>


To download the software and retrieve license keys:

<ol>
<li>
Visit the following URL:

<pre>
   http://www.genworks.com/dl
</pre>
</li>

<li>
Enter your email address. If you don't have an email address on file with Genworks, 
send email to licensing -at- genworks -dot- com
</li>


<li>
Read and accept the applicable license agreement and click the checkbox
</li>

<li>
Click the link to download the .zip or .exe install file, and start
the download to a known location on your computer.
</li>

<li>
Click the "Retrieve License Key" link, to have your license key file(s)
emailed to you.
</li>

</ol>


<p>
GDL is currently distributed for all the platforms as a self-contained
"zip" file which does not requiring official administrator
installation, or an install executable ("exe") file.

To install the downloaded software, you can either:

<ul>
<li>unzip the "zip" file to a known location</li>
or
<li>run the installer executable (exe) file and follow the prompts</li>
</ul>


After the GDL application directory is in place (typically in
"c:/Program Files" on Windows, or "/usr/local/" on Linux), you have to
copy your license file into that GDL application directory. The
license file was obtained via email in a previous step, and should be
named either "devel.lic" for Enterprise or Student editions, or
"gdl.lic" for Professional/Trial versions.


Now you can start the GDL development environment by running the
included "run-gdl.bat" startup script (Windows) or "run-gdl" script
(Linux/Mac).
</p>


NOTE on Windows, the Start Menu item which gets installed by the
Windows installation is not the usual way to start GDL (it will start
it without Emacs, which is not what you normally want). This will be
updated in a future release, but to start GDL with emacs, you should
simply navigate to the GDL installation directory and run the batch
file:

<pre>

   run-gdl.bat
   
</pre>

This will start Emacs and should give you the welcome screen with
instructions for starting GDL itself within Emacs.

</p>





 </clix:chapter>


 <clix:chapter name="emacs" title="Getting Started with Emacs">

<i>(Note -- a license key file is not required in order to get started
with Emacs) </i>

<p>
Start Emacs with the GDL environment with the "run-gdl.bat" script
(Windows) or the "run-gdl" shell-script (Linux). Emacs should come up
with instructions for:


<ol>
<li> doing the Emacs tutorial, </li>
<li> starting the GDL process, and </li>
<li> special keychord shortcuts for working with GDL </li>
</ol>

</p>

 </clix:chapter>


 <clix:chapter name="cl" title="Getting Started with Common Lisp">

The following resources should provide sufficient CL background to start
with GDL:

<ul>

<li> <a href="blt.pdf"> Basic Lisp Techniques</a> (Chapters 1, 2, 3)</li>

<li> <a href="http://www.genworks.com/training-g101"> Online CL Training
Slides</a> <i>(designed to be used with lecture)</i></li>

<li><a href="http://www.norvig.com/luv-slides.ps"> Norvig and Pitman Lisp Style Guide </a></li>

<li> <a href="http://www.franz.com/support/documentation/current/ansicl/ansicl.htm"> Full ANSI Common Lisp Specification</a> <i>(for later reference)</i></li>


</ul>


 </clix:chapter>

 <clix:chapter name="gdl-start" title="Getting Started with GDL Itself">

<ul>
<li><a href="gdl-tutorial.pdf">GDL Tutorial</a>
<i>A Tutorial for GDL. This tutorial is somewhat outdated and we hope to
have it revised relatively soon, but it still gives a decent overview
of the fundamentals.</i></li>
<li> <a href="http://www.genworks.com/training-g102"> Online GDL Training
Slides</a> <i>(designed to be used with lecture)</i></li>

</ul>


 </clix:chapter>

 <clix:chapter name="gdl-reference" title="Reference Documentation for GDL Objects, Operators, and Parameters">

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.genworks.com/downloads/customer-documentation/reference/index.html">GDL Reference</a>
<i>This is where you will spend 95% of your time after you are
familiar with the basics. This documentation is auto-generated from
GDL when we do the builds, so it gets updated with every new patch
release. We are also working on a context-sensitive interface to this
documentation from the live Emacs editing session. For now you have to
refer to the Web version, and look up the object, message, or operator
you want to know about.</i></li>

</ul>

 </clix:chapter>


 <clix:chapter name="other-doc" title="Other Documentation and Reference">

Currently, some of these files are in PDF format, some of the files
are plaintext, and some are linked HTML.


<ul>

<li><a href="bootstrap.txt">Managing Projects</a>
<i>Utilities for compiling and loading your GDL codebases.</i>
</li>

<li><a href="usage.txt">GDL Usage</a>
<i>Concise GDL Language Specification.</i></li>

<li><a href="gwl-usage.txt">GWL Usage</a>
<i>Concise syntax guide to Web User Interface layer -- currently being updated for new GDL Ajax features</i></li>

<li><a href="ta2.html">Testing and Tracking Utility (Ta2)</a>
<i>Overview of GDL's graphical development testing and inspection utility -- this will soon be replaced with a functionally equivalent, but CSS-styled, upgrade, name yet to be determined.</i></li>

<li><a href="make-gdl-app.txt">Generating Runtime Applications</a>
<i>Generating runtime GDL and GDL/GWL applications (this is under construction, 
to be released with 1577 Enterprise)</i></li>

<li><a href="output-formats.txt">Output Formats and Lenses</a>
<i>Creating output from GDL objects in various formats.</i></li>

<li><a href="drawing.txt">GDL Drawing Package</a>
<i>Creating Engineering Drawings with Dimensions and Annotations, as well as Typeset Text Blocks</i></li>

<li><a href="reserved.txt">Reserved Symbols</a>
<i>A listing of certain symbols you should avoid using as message names in your own apps, 
to avoid clashes with pre-defined GDL/GWL message names.</i></li>

<li><a href="translators.txt">Conversion Tools</a>
<i>Conversion tools for object-oriented code in legacy Lisp-based and KBE formats.</i></li>

</ul>

 </clix:chapter>

 <clix:chapter name="support" title="Customer Support">

<p>
<b>Evaluation and Student Licensees are not entitled to support directly
from Genworks.</b> -- Please register for
the <a href="http://groups.google.com/group/genworks">Genworks Google
Group</a> then post your questions there.
</p>

<p>

For commercial licensees, Genworks Customer support is usually
available on U.S. business days from 9am to 5pm Michigan time (Eastern
Standard Time, same as New York). Support for all included components
of GDL/GWL is provided by Genworks as your single point of
contact. Our VAR agreements with vendors such as Franz Inc. and SMS
stipulate that Genworks' customers contact only Genworks for support,
and not e.g. Franz Inc. or SMS directly. As necessary Genworks will
follow up with our vendors for second-level support on Allegro CL,
SMLib, etc.
</p>

<p>

Genworks Technical Support can be reached at:
<ul>
<li>support@genworks.com</li>
<li>+1 248-330-2979</li> (telephone for emergencies only, please).
</ul></p>


 </clix:chapter>

 <clix:chapter name="copyright-legal" title="Copyright/Legal Notice">

<small><i>

All information contained in this documentation set is copyright
(c) 2009, Genworks International, and is intended exclusively for
use in operating a properly licensed installation of the Genworks
GDL/GWL product.

It may not be redistributed or otherwise used for any other purpose.

</i></small>

 </clix:chapter>




</clix:documentation>
